let's design the high level architecture
of Twitter I mean how hard Could It Be
by the way this video is taken from my
ongoing course system design interview
which will be complete by the end of
this month you can check it out on
neco.io before we get started I do want
to mention Twitter has been quite a
popular topic recently especially the
underlying infrastructure and design but
keep in mind that in a real interview
Your Design does not have to exactly
match the product that's not what it's
about at all it's about discussing the
trade-offs and kind of demonstrating
your knowledge of being able to weigh
the pros and cons of an approach and of
course there's many similar products to
Twitter there really isn't any one
correct approach so we don't have to
actually replicate the real Twitter
design unless of course you're
interviewing at Twitter in that case you
might have to because they recently
fired everyone so they need people to
know how it works so let's start with
the background we know that Twitter is a
social network first and foremost where
some people can follow other people and
that relationship can be be mutual this
person can also follow the other person
but some people might end up with more
followers than others right so assume
that one person is really popular and
everybody wants to read all of their
tweets but you know most people on
Twitter probably aren't actually
tweeting very often most people don't
actually have many followers including
myself I'm mentioning this because it
kind of hints that this is going to be a
very read heavy system and of course on
Twitter the whole point is that people
can create tweets so on a particular
tweet you have a person like this is
their profile picture and their username
and then the actual content of the tweet
it can have some text it can have some
images and it can have a video there's a
lot of things you can do to interact
with a tweet of course you can like the
Tweet you can do a retweet you can
follow the person who actually made the
Tweet or unfollow them recently you can
even edit tweets now but this is just to
give you a general idea of what kind of
functionality you might want to clarify
with your interviewer so now actually
digging into the functional requirements
Twitter is very very large of course we
can't design every little piece of
functionality in a 45 minute interview
so what exactly do we want to spend most
of our time on and what parts can we
just kind of hand wave and dismiss and
just briefly discuss let's say the first
feature the priority feature is that we
want to be able to follow other users so
users can follow each other now there's
no point of following other people if
you can't actually create tweets so
that's also going to be just as
important and then third is actually
viewing a news feed now at a basic level
these two features are pretty simple but
viewing a feed can definitely be more
complicated especially when we get into
how we want to rank that feed what kind
of algorithm are we going to use
probably there's machine learning going
on in there and in many cases you end up
seeing Tweets in your feed by people
that you're not even following but we're
gonna assume that that's not the case
for reviewing a feed we just want to see
tweets of people that we actually follow
I think that would be something worth
clarifying with your interviewer that's
something that can kind of scope down
this interview because you might assume
that we're doing something really
complicated but your interviewer is
actually looking for something more
simple that's a trap that you don't want
to fall into now what exactly is going
to go in the Tweet itself we know that
Twitter actually has a limit on tweet
size I think it's 140 characters let's
assume that your interviewer gives you
that number but at the same time with
social networks of course we end up with
images and videos and let's say that yes
we are going to include these in our
design so now let's transition into the
non-functional requirements which is not
going to be completely separate from
these actual features we're implementing
the first thing you probably want to
know is how many users we're talking
about here let's say the number is 500
million total users but in terms of
daily active users we have about 200
million of them that are daily active I
think that's pretty close to the real
number but remember the real number
isn't so important I think the main
observation here is that almost half
half of the users are active so when we
actually create feeds for users we'll be
doing it for most users most people are
going to be logging on most people are
going to be viewing their feed well not
most but nearly half which is a pretty
large percentage about 40 percent Now
While most people will be viewing their
feed they probably won't be creating
tweets but again this is something we
have to clarify let's say of those 200
million daily active users each of them
will read about a hundred tweets per day
so 200 million times a hundred that's
going to be 20 billion tweet reads per
day now what is the size of each tweet
if we have 140 characters that's about
140 bytes but let's assume that there's
additional information with a tweet we
have the username of that tweet and
possibly there's a lot more metadata to
be safe or just a basic tweet that just
includes text we can assume that for
each tweet we have to do a kilobyte of
reading from our storage now we also
know that some tweets can contain images
and videos so on average this is going
to be higher how much higher we could
spend a lot of time digging into the
math you could ask your interviewer a
bunch of questions but most likely this
is not what they want you to spend time
on let's just average this up to a
megabyte because maybe videos on average
are 10 megabytes if they're a bit longer
which I don't know what the limit is for
a video length on Twitter but it could
be reasonably high but we also know that
few tweets are going to actually have
this so we average it down to this
because most tweets are going to be
about a kilobyte let's say so let's say
a megabyte per each tweet so how much
data are we going to be reading if it's
20 billion tweets a megabyte for each
tweet that is quite a lot of data so if
each tweet was just one byte 20 billion
that's going to be 20 Gigabytes but now
we're actually multiplying this by a
megabyte which is a million so multiply
this by a thousand we get 20 terabytes
but we have to multiply it by a thousand
again because that's you know what a
million is and then we get to 20
petabytes so overall we're going to be
reading 20 petabytes of data per day now
it's no surprise to us that this is
going to be a read heavy system this is
kind of hinting to us what type of
storage solution should we use we
probably don't need to be strongly
consistent eventual consistency is
enough and that brings us to how much
are we going to be writing per day how
many tweets are we going to be creating
per day well we have 200 million daily
active users so let's say a reasonable
number is 50 million tweets created per
day most people aren't going to be
creating tweets but maybe some people
create 10 tweets per day so this is a
decent number but you're not going to be
guessing this your interviewer should be
giving you something reasonable now we
could go through the rest of the math
with this number and I can show you that
we're going to be writing much less than
20 petabytes of data per day especially
if we don't include the images and
videos which we're probably not going to
be directly storing in a database but
the main thing here to realize is that
yes we're going to be writing much less
than we're reading so that's how we want
to optimize our design and let's say
that the average user follow those about
a hundred people so a hundred follows
per person but of course there can be
power users who have a thousand or ten
thousand people that they follow but the
more important consideration here is for
a user how many followers can they have
someone like Kim Kardashian I don't know
if she's the most popular on Twitter but
I think it's at least over a hundred
million followers that they have so this
is the more important consideration
people who have a massive amount of
followers so the question is going to be
for all the people that follow Kim
Kardashian how are they gonna get the
tweets this is kind of hinting to us
that wherever we're storing her tweets
it's gonna get overloaded pretty quickly
so now that we kind of know what we're
looking for let's get into the high
level design we know of course that
everything is going to start with our
client whether that's a computer or a
mobile device it doesn't really matter
for us we're focusing on the back end
which is agnostic to the front end we
know the first thing our user is going
to be hitting is the application servers
to perform actions like creating a tweet
or getting their news feed or following
someone now because of the scale that
we're dealing with we're probably going
to be bottlenecked by getting the news
feed that's what's going to be happening
most frequently and if we want to scale
this up assuming that these application
servers are stateless it should be easy
to scale them up and of course we will
have the load balancer in between this
that's pretty hand wavy I mean that's
something you can just memorize and say
well if you want to scale horizontally
scale this and put a load balancer in
there it's pretty trivial so I'm not
going to spend a lot of time on that now
of course our application server is
going to be reading from some storage
let's say we do have a database and
let's say that it is a relational
database and you might be thinking if
we're going to be doing read heavy why
use a relational database why not just
have a nosql database well it depends on
what type of data we're going to be
storing do we need joins in this case
and we could because we do have a very
relational model when it comes to
following that's a pretty clear
relationship between followers and
follow ease so that's a reason to go
with a relational database now in theory
you it would be easier to scale a nosql
database but we can Implement sharding
with a relational database so that does
give us some flexibility though after
finishing our high level design we might
want to revise this because we could
just store tweets and user information
in a nosql database and then have the
graph DB which would be very easy to
find that follower relationship because
a graph DB is essentially like an
adjacency list graph where every person
is like a node in a graph and to find
all the people that they follow you just
have to look at every outgoing Edge and
to find all the followers of a person
you just have to look at every incoming
Edge so depending on your expertise and
your background and of course what your
interviewer is looking for and what they
might be familiar with you can kind of
have some discussion about these
differences now with the massive amount
of reads that we're going to be doing we
basically have to have a caching layer
in between so as we're reading tweets we
will be hitting our cache before we hit
our database but also remember that we
are going to be storing media so we need
a separate storage solution for that
media related National databases aren't
the best for that so we'll have some
type of object storage for that
something like Google Cloud Storage or
Amazon S3 so when we actually read a
tweet we'll be getting the information
about that tweet like the Tweet ID who's
the creator of that tweet what time was
it created whether it included an image
or not what was the image that it
included the profile picture of the
person who made it the application
server can then fetch the image like the
profile picture or the video that showed
up in that tweet and it can do that
separately but at the same time because
these assets are static in nature it may
be better to actually distribute them
over a CDN Network so then actually our
application server does not have to
interact with the object storage the
application server will respond to the
user with all the information that they
need including the URL of that image or
video that they need and then the client
whether they're using a mobile device or
a desktop browser will make a separate
request which will actually hit our CDN
Network which is tied to our object
storage what type of algorithm would we
use in this case well even though we're
looking at the high level right now we
probably want to use a poll based CDN we
don't want to necessarily push every
image or video to the CDN immediately
also remember the benefit of a CDN is
that it's geographically located close
to the user we know that people in India
might be looking at different types of
tweets and images and videos than people
in the United States so it doesn't make
sense to put every single new tweet push
it directly to the CDN Network and with
a pull-based CDN we kind of guarantee
that the stuff that's loaded onto our
CDN is the relevant stuff that people
want to see anyway the popular things so
now let's spend most of our time
actually digging into the details which
some people like to start out with the
interface that we'll be using we will
have a couple so remember we have a
create tweet there could be a lot of
metadata sent with that request of
course the user ID of the person
creating the Tweet but mainly the user
is actually responsible for sending the
content of the tweets so one is the
actual text and then second is going to
be the actual media of course every
tweet has a created timestamp but we
assume that that will be handled server
side and every tweet has to be
identified but we'll assume that the
Tweet ID is also created server side and
of course the user ID of the person
that's actually creating it well we'll
assume that in the header of the HTTP
request that there's some authorization
token for us to know that the correct
person is making the Tweet but we could
also have the user ID passed into this
request or the username of the person
and next of course we have getting the
actual feed and that really doesn't need
any information at all that's a very
basic read request we don't need to send
additional data that we're going to be
actually storing get feed should just
pass in the user ID so that we know
which person's feed are we getting but
at the same time I should not be able to
pass in your user ID even if I know it
to get your user feed there's nothing
that can go super wrong with that but it
shouldn't be allowed and that would be
handled by the HTTP header we know that
that there's actual authentication going
on in this system it's just that we're
not focusing on that we're focusing on
the actual Twitter design authentication
happens with pretty much every
application and we also have the follow
interaction so a user can follow another
person they'll pass in their user ID and
maybe the username of the person that
they're trying to follow so these are
the three main interactions now how are
we actually going to be storing this
data in particular we're going to be
storing two things the actual tweets so
assuming we have a relational database
we'll have a table of tweets and we'll
also have a table of follows so the
follow relationship is pretty simple you
have the follow e the person who's
following the other person that's going
to be a string and we'll have another
the actual follow ER I think I misspoke
when I was describing followey so the
follower is the person that's following
the following the follow e is the one
that's being followed now assuming that
this is a table and remember for a user
we want to get all the tweets of people
that this person follows so they're the
follower and they want all the tweets of
their followers how would we Index this
table we'd probably want to index based
on the follower because then all records
in that table will be grouped together
based on the follower so all the people
that this guy follows will be grouped
together in the table it'll just be a
range query so assuming this is our
table all records for this person will
be grouped together in a particular
range over here I think it's worth
mentioning that we would favor indexing
based on the follower if we have a read
heavy system now for the Tweet itself we
kind of briefly talked about it of
course we're gonna have the Tweet ID
we're going to have the time stamp we're
gonna have the user ID of the person who
created it and we're gonna have the
content of the Tweet whether it's the
text which technically could be empty if
we have some media attached to it but we
actually won't be storing the media
itself in the database we'll have a
reference to that media that references
the object store now the bigger problem
with our storage is we're going to be
storing a massive amount of data if you
went through the calculation that I
mentioned earlier you would have gotten
to I think roughly 50 gigabytes of data
are going to be written per day to our
relational database if we're not
including the media so that's a lot of
data in a month we'll have I think 1.5
terabytes in the course of a year will
have roughly 18 terabytes so it is a
large amount of data but it's actually
reasonable and the good thing about
Twitter is that tweets are relatively
small but the problem is we're going to
be having so many reads hitting this
database a person is going to be reading
a hundred tweets per day and we have 200
million of them so the first approach
and the obvious thing to do is to have
read only replicas of this database if
reads are the bottleneck it's not hard
to just add additional database
instances now the problem will be when a
user actually creates a tweet if we have
single leader replication all those
rights are going to be hitting a single
database and remember if we have 50
million writes per day you divide that
by a hundred thousand which is roughly
the amount of seconds in a day we get
500 rights per second well probably even
more than that but at the same time
there's gonna be moments where we have
traffic this is the average but Peak
could be much higher I mean Peak could
be even 10 times this amount depending
on what's going on maybe Elon Musk does
something crazy so ideally we should be
able to scale our rights as well and the
obvious way to do this is by using
sharding but the question is how are we
going to be implementing this sharding
before we get into that I forgot to
mention if we do have read-only replicas
it's okay if a single instance gets the
rights and then asynchronously populates
the read-only replicas with the data
because in the case that a user ends up
hitting one of the replicas and gets
some stale data it's okay if it takes
five seconds after a tweet is created
before a user actually gets that tweet
or it might even take 20 seconds that
would wouldn't be ideal but it's not the
end of the world with something like
Twitter now the question is how are we
actually going to be sharding this what
type of Shard key are we going to be
using I think the most obvious and easy
way would be to do it based on user ID
because that's kind of the whole point
of our design the way we scoped it out a
user only cares about a subset of users
they don't care about every user it
doesn't make a lot of sense to do it
based on tweet ID because what we want
is to break up our database into pieces
and we want a particular user to ideally
only have to hit one of these pieces
with the logic of our system especially
the sharding logic a user should know
which people they follow and then we can
route the request to the appropriate
shards that contain the tweets of the
people that they follow and we'll know
that because we can use our Shard key to
determine that but if we break up the
tweets based on tweet ID we actually
don't know which Shard contains the
tweets of the people that they follow so
we'd have to query all the shards that
kind of defeats the purpose so we'll be
choosing to do this based on user ID and
since we don't actually have complex
queries and joins that we're doing to
actually retrieve the tweets how will we
get the people that they follow well if
we Shard that based on user ID as well
all the people that this guy follows
should be on A Single Shard now a
potential problem is that we will
actually have to order the tweets just
fetching the tweets is not enough we
will actually have to query them and
then order them based on the time that
they were created and of course how many
tweets are we looking for if we're just
looking for a small number like 20 what
if the user wants to scroll down in
their feed and we want 20 more tweets we
don't necessarily need to get all tweets
immediately we need to wait for the user
to actually scroll or maybe we can
actually get all the tweets immediately
but before I even get into that let's
quickly look at how our current system
is going to work when a user creates an
essentially it will go through the
server based on the user ID we will find
the appropriate Shard and then store the
tweet on that Shard and then any images
and media on object storage as users
view their feed we may have to query
multiple shards to find all the relevant
tweets and then order them and then send
them back to the user that could
definitely be very slow that's clearly
the bottleneck here now we do have a
caching layer and in theory the most
popular tweets will be stored already on
this caching layer and if they're not
then we can have some type of lru
algorithm working here because we care
about the most recent tweets most likely
people aren't going to be viewing tweets
from a year ago even if they had like a
billion views after a while people get
tired of them lru might be better here
and in theory caching should definitely
help us lower the latency but remember
different people will have different
tweets we definitely can't guarantee
that all 20 tweets that this person
wants to see are already going to be
cached what if 19 of them are already
cashed and then that last one tweet we
still have to go and read disk to get
that tweet and while you're scrolling
maybe all your tweets are loaded but one
tweet in the middle is taking a few
extra seconds that's not a great user
experience so the problem we're running
into is not really scalability it's
latency and caching helps with that and
sharding also helps with that that's
kind of the point of sharding with
read-only replicas we're able to handle
scale but as we break up the data into
smaller chunks then we can also lower
latency because we're going to be
querying a smaller amount of data but we
still may have to query multiple shards
to get this latency even lower we can
get pretty creative and we can actually
generate the news feed of users
asynchronously and we would do that for
every single user in theory because we
know a large amount of the users 200
million out of 500 million are actually
active it makes sense to generate the
news feed for all of them even if 60
percent of them aren't going to actually
view it it's not a ton of wasted work
and we could also tune it such that we
only regenerate the news feed for people
that are actually active within the last
30 days now at a very high level what we
can do is have some kind of message
queue or Pub sub system which will take
every new tweet that is created will
also not just be written to the database
but it will be sent from the app servers
to the pub sub queue and this queue will
feed into a cluster something like a
spark cluster but the point is that
these workers will in parallel process
all the messages that we're getting
which will include every time there's a
new tweet that is generated there could
be a lot so we need to do this
asynchronously and the point of this is
that these will basically feed into a
new cache and this cache will be
responsible for actually storing the
user feed so now when a user loads their
home page and gets their list of 20
tweets the application server will will
actually be hitting this feed cache
maybe this cache is used for individual
tweets that are maybe embedded on
websites or sometimes you just open up
an individual tweet not in the context
of a user feed and you want to maybe
look at the replies of that tweet but
this is starting to make a little bit
less sense or even having this cache so
I'm just kind of giving some possible
use cases but this is the cache that
will actually have a feed for every
single user so if this is in memory it
may have a large amount of data now we
have 200 million users and if we want to
have 100 tweets for every single user it
could be a very large amount so we
probably want to Shard this similar to
how we did with our relational database
but the point is that this will
definitely lower the latency because the
feeds are not generated as a user
actually requests to actually get the
feed we don't have to actually run a
complex query on our relational database
having to query multiple shards and then
joining the results together based on
the time that they were created and then
ordering them like that the feed will
actually all already be created now the
complicated part is actually updating
the Tweet we kind of went through the
flow of when a tweet is created it will
be added to the message queue and then
for that individual tweet these workers
will add that tweet to all the feeds of
people that are following the author of
that tweet but now the problem is if
somebody has a hundred followers then
these workers will have to update a
hundred feeds but what about somebody
like Kim Kardashian who has maybe a
hundred million followers updating a
hundred million feeds every single time
somebody popular like that makes a tweet
is very very expensive maybe in that
case it's not the end of the world for
us to actually have to update the feed
of that user at the time that they
actually request it big somebody could
have a hundred million followers and us
having to update 100 million feeds every
time they make a tweet is pretty
expensive but not all 100 million of
those followers are even loading their
feed every single day so it'd probably
be easier to do that work as it's needed
so when a user makes a request they get
their feed but maybe in parallel to that
our app server could look for other
tweets probably a popular tweet by
somebody like that is already cached
here so then at that point our
application server would also update the
feed of that user now what gets even
more complicated is what happens when a
user follows somebody new their feed has
to be updated in that case as well now
it's okay we can tolerate a few seconds
maybe five or ten seconds before their
feed is actually updated but it does
have to get updated nonetheless and we
would have sort of a similar mechanism
where a user follows somebody new we add
a message to a message queue we have a
bunch of workers that then have to
update the feed cache of the person who
just followed somebody else and by the
way this cluster of course is going to
actually have to read our database as
well which actually has the tweets
themselves remember the whole point of
doing this is to lower the latent agency
when somebody opens up their home page
and they want to see 20 tweets we want
it to be as quick as possible and all
this complexity arises from that if we
can tolerate a few more seconds we can
simplify our design but as long as this
discussion has already been I want to
say that all of this has actually been
pretty high level things can get much
more complicated and this is actually
definitely not exactly how Twitter is
designed there are actually problems
with this design as well there could be
concurrent updates to our cache there's
a lot of details that we haven't
discussed how would the ordering of the
feed even be in this case when somebody
loads 20 tweets they want to see 20 more
we obviously have to paginate that and
there's a ton more details that we could
have gone into the main takeaway though
here is that Twitter definitely cannot
be designed or built in a weekend
designing these large-scale systems is a
very complicated task even Engineers who
worked at Twitter for years still ran
into issues where they had to modify
designs and if you read some of the
white papers from 2 2010 up until now
they actually did they changed parts of
their database how they were storing
relations how they were storing who
follows who so with that I encourage you
to read some of the official papers that
the engineering teams at Twitter have
written if you'd like to learn more
because while things can get complicated
they are still pretty interesting